<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lionel Rigoux</title>
    <description>Some description here.
</description>
    <link>http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2017 10:31:15 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2017 10:31:15 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Neurocomputational account of how the human brain decides when to have a break</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;No pain, no gain: cost-benefit trade-off has been formalized in classical decision theory to account for how we choose whether to engage effort. However, how the brain decides when to have breaks in the course of effort production remains poorly understood. We propose that decisions to cease and resume work are triggered by a cost evidence accumulation signal reaching upper and lower bounds, respectively. We developed a task in which participants are free to exert a physical effort knowing that their payoff would be proportional to their effort duration. Functional MRI and magnetoencephalography recordings conjointly revealed that the theoretical cost evidence accumulation signal was expressed in proprioceptive regions (bilateral posterior insula). Furthermore, the slopes and bounds of the accumulation process were adapted to the difficulty of the task and the money at stake. Cost evidence accumulation might therefore provide a dynamical mechanistic account of how the human brain maximizes benefits while preventing exhaustion.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/16/PNAS-2013/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/16/PNAS-2013/</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>VBA - a probabilistic treatment of nonlinear models for neurobiological and behavioural data</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This work is in line with an on-going effort tending toward a computational (quantitative and refutable) understanding of human neuro-cognitive processes. Many sophisticated models for behavioural and neurobiological data have flourished during the past decade. Most of these models are partly unspecified (i.e. they have unknown parameters) and nonlinear. This makes them difficult to peer with a formal statistical data analysis framework. In turn, this compromises the reproducibility of model-based empirical studies. This work exposes a software toolbox that provides generic, efficient and robust probabilistic solutions to the three problems of model-based analysis of empirical data: (i) data simulation, (ii) parameter estimation/model selection, and (iii) experimental design optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/16/PCB-2014/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/16/PCB-2014/</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A model of reward-and effort-based optimal decision making and motor control</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Costs (e.g. energetic expenditure) and benefits (e.g. food) are central determinants of behavior. In ecology and economics, they are combined to form a utility function which is maximized to guide choices. This principle is widely used in neuroscience as a normative model of decision and action, but current versions of this model fail to consider how decisions are actually converted into actions (i.e. the formation of trajectories). Here, we describe an approach where decision making and motor control are optimal, iterative processes derived from the maximization of the discounted, weighted difference between expected rewards and foreseeable motor efforts. The model accounts for decision making in cost/benefit situations, and detailed characteristics of control and goal tracking in realistic motor tasks. As a normative construction, the model is relevant to address the neural bases and pathological aspects of decision making and motor control.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/16/PCB-2012/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/16/PCB-2012/</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bayesian model selection for group studies—Revisited</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we revisit the problem of Bayesian model selection (BMS) at the group level. We originally addressed this issue in Stephan et al. (2009), where models are treated as random effects that could differ between subjects, with an unknown population distribution. Here, we extend this work, by (i) introducing the Bayesian omnibus risk (BOR) as a measure of the statistical risk incurred when performing group BMS, (ii) highlighting the difference between random effects BMS and classical random effects analyses of parameter estimates, and (iii) addressing the problem of between group or condition model comparisons. We address the first issue by quantifying the chance likelihood of apparent differences in model frequencies. This leads to the notion of protected exceedance probabilities. The second issue arises when people want to ask “whether a model parameter is zero or not” at the group level. Here, we provide guidance as to whether to use a classical second-level analysis of parameter estimates, or random effects BMS. The third issue rests on the evidence for a difference in model labels or frequencies across groups or conditions. Overall, we hope that the material presented in this paper finesses the problems of group-level BMS in the analysis of neuroimaging and behavioural data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/16/Neuroimage-2014/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/16/Neuroimage-2014/</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Confidence and psychosis - a neuro-computational account of contingency learning disruption by NMDA blockade</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A state of pathological uncertainty about environmental regularities might represent a key step in the pathway to psychotic illness. Early psychosis can be investigated in healthy volunteers under ketamine, an NMDA receptor antagonist. Here, we explored the effects of ketamine on contingency learning using a placebo-controlled, double-blind, crossover design. During functional magnetic resonance imaging, participants performed an instrumental learning task, in which cue-outcome contingencies were probabilistic and reversed between blocks. Bayesian model comparison indicated that in such an unstable environment, reinforcement learning parameters are downregulated depending on confidence level, an adaptive mechanism that was specifically disrupted by ketamine administration. Drug effects were underpinned by altered neural activity in a fronto-parietal network, which reflected the confidence-based shift to exploitation of learned contingencies. Our findings suggest that an early characteristic of psychosis lies in a persistent doubt that undermines the stabilization of behavioral policy resulting in a failure to exploit regularities in the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/16/MolecularPsychiatry-2015/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/16/MolecularPsychiatry-2015/</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Obesity-Predisposing Variant of the FTO Gene Regulates D2R-Dependent Reward Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Variations in the fat mass and obesity-associated (FTO) gene are linked to obesity. However, the underlying neurobiological mechanisms by which these genetic variants influence obesity, behavior, and brain are unknown. Given that Fto regulates D2/3R signaling in mice, we tested in humans whether variants in FTO would interact with a variant in the ANKK1 gene, which alters D2R signaling and is also associated with obesity. In a behavioral and fMRI study, we demonstrate that gene variants of FTO affect dopamine (D2)-dependent midbrain brain responses to reward learning and behavioral responses associated with learning from negative outcome in humans. Furthermore, dynamic causal modeling confirmed that FTO variants modulate the connectivity in a basic reward circuit of meso-striato-prefrontal regions, suggesting a mechanism by which genetic predisposition alters reward processing not only in obesity, but also in other disorders with altered D2R-dependent impulse control, such as addiction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/16/JNeuroSci-2015/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/16/JNeuroSci-2015/</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dynamic Causal Modelling of Brain-Behaviour Relationships</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this work, we expose a mathematical treatment of brain-behaviour relationships, which we coin behavioural Dynamic Causal Modelling or bDCM. This approach aims at decomposing the brain’s transformation of stimuli into behavioural outcomes, in terms of the relative contribution of brain regions and their connections. In brief, bDCM places the brain at the interplay between stimulus and behaviour: behavioural outcomes arise from coordinated activity in (hidden) neural networks, whose dynamics are driven by experimental inputs. Estimating neural parameters that control network connectivity and plasticity effectively performs a neurobiologically-constrained approximation to the brain’s input-outcome transform. In other words, neuroimaging data essentially serves to enforce the realism of bDCM’s decomposition of input-output relationships. In addition, post-hoc artificial lesions analyses allow us to predict induced behavioural deficits and quantify the importance of network features for funnelling input-output relationships. This is important, because this enables one to bridge the gap with neuropsychological studies of brain-damaged patients. We demonstrate the face validity of the approach using Monte-Carlo simulations, and its predictive validity using empirical fMRI/behavioural data from an inhibitory control task. Lastly, we discuss promising applications of this work, including the assessment of functional degeneracy (in the healthy brain) and the prediction of functional recovery after lesions (in neurological patients).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/15/Neuroimage-2015/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/publications/2015/10/15/Neuroimage-2015/</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>VBA toolbox</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/project/2015/06/08/VBA-toolbox/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/project/2015/06/08/VBA-toolbox/</guid>
        
        
        <category>project</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Army Knife</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/project/2015/05/15/army-knife/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lionel-rigoux.github.io/project/2015/05/15/army-knife/</guid>
        
        
        <category>project</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
